So since I was here last in '06,
حسنا، منذ ان كنت هنا اخر مرة في 2006
we discovered that global climate change
اكتشفنا ان تغيير المناخ العالمي
is turning out to be a pretty serious issue,
قد اتضح انه قضية خطيرة
so we covered that fairly extensively
لذلك قمنا بتغطية الموضوع على نطاق واسع
in Skeptic magazine.
بمجلة سكيبتك (المتشككون)
We investigate all kinds
قمنا بالتحقيق في كل انواع
of scientific and quasi-scientific controversies,
التناقضات العلمية و شبه العلمية
but it turns out we don't have to worry about any of this
و لكن تبين انه لا داعي للقلق حول اي من هذا
because the world's going to end in 2012.
لأن العالم سينتهي في 2012
Another update:
تحديث اخر:
You will recall I introduced you guys
لعلكم تذكرون عندما عرفتكم
to the Quadro Tracker.
على متعقب كوادرو
It's like a water dowsing device.
انه كجهاز الغطس في المياه
It's just a hollow piece of plastic with an antenna that swivels around.
انها قطعة من البلاستيك جوفاء مع هوائي يدور حولها
And you walk around, and it points to things.
وبينما تتجول انت، تشير هي الى أشياء.
Like if you're looking for marijuana in students' lockers,
مثلا اذا كنت تبحث عن الماريجوانا في خزائن الطلبة.
it'll point right to somebody.
ستشير فورا الى شخص ما.
Oh, sorry. (Laughter)
اه، اسف. (ضحك)
This particular one that was given to me
هذه القطعة بالتحديد التي اعطيت لي
finds golf balls,
تجد كرات الغولف
especially if you're at a golf course
خاصة ان كنت في ملعب للغولف
and you check under enough bushes.
و تقوم بالبحث تحت الشجيرات بما فيه الكفاية
Well, under the category of "What's the harm of silly stuff like this?"
حسنا، تحت اطار فئة " ماهو الضرر من اشياء سخيفة كهذه؟"
this device, the ADE 651,
هذا الجهاز، ايه دي اي 651،
was sold to the Iraqi government
تم بيعه الى الحكومة العراقية
for 40,000 dollars apiece.
بمبلغ 40,000 دولار للقطعة الواحدة
It's just like this one, completely worthless,
مجرد قطعة كهذه، لا قيمة لها تماما
in which it allegedly worked by "electrostatic
حيث يزعم انها تعمل بكهرباء
magnetic ion attraction,"
جذب الايونات المغناطيسية
which translates to
وهو ما يترجم الى
"pseudoscientific baloney" -- would be the nice word --
"هراء علمي زائف"-- لتكن هذه الكلمة اللطيفة--
in which you string together a bunch of words that sound good,
عندما تقوم بصياغة مجموعة من الكلمات التي تبدو جيدة معا
but it does absolutely nothing.
ولكن لا فائدة منها على الاطلاق
In this case, at trespass points,
في هذه الحالة عند نقاط العبور،
allowing people to go through
السماح لاشخاص بالمرور
because your little tracker device said they were okay,
لان جهازك الصغير للتعقب يوافق على ذلك
actually cost lives.
قد يكلف ارواحا
So there is a danger to pseudoscience,
اذن هنالك اخطار للهراء العلمي الزائف
in believing in this sort of thing.
في تصديق مثل هذه الاشياء
So what I want to talk about today is belief.
ما اريد ان اتحدث عنه اليوم هو الايمان (التصديق)
I want to believe,
انا اريد ان اصدق
and you do too.
وانت ايضا تريد ذلك
And in fact, I think my thesis here is that
في الواقع اعتقد ان رسالتي هنا هي
belief is the natural state of things.
ان التصديق هوالحالة الطبيعية للامور
It is the default option. We just believe.
انه الخيار الفطري، نحن نصدق بالفطرة
We believe all sorts of things.
نصدق كل انواع الاشياء
Belief is natural;
التصديق هو امر طبيعي
disbelief, skepticism, science, is not natural.
اما عدم التصديق، التشكيك، العلوم فهي امور غير طبيعية
It's more difficult.
انها اكثر تعقيدا
It's uncomfortable to not believe things.
انه من غير المريح ان لاتصدق الاشياء
So like Fox Mulder on "X-Files,"
مثل شخصية فوكس مولدر ببرنامج "اكس فايلز"
who wants to believe in UFOs? Well, we all do,
من يريد ان يعتقد بوجود الاطباق الطائرة؟ حسنا كلنا نريد
and the reason for that is because
والسبب وراء ذلك هو
we have a belief engine in our brains.
اننا نمتلك محركات للتصديق داخل عقولنا
Essentially, we are pattern-seeking primates.
في الاساس، نحن كائنات باحثة عن النمط
We connect the dots: A is connected to B; B is connected to C.
نحن نربط النقاط: النقطة أ مرتبطة بالنقطة ب والنقطة ب بالنقطة ج.
And sometimes A really is connected to B,
وفي بعض الاحيان تكون النقطة أ مرتبطة فعلا بالنقطة ب.
and that's called association learning.
وهذا مايسمى بالتعلم العلائقي
We find patterns, we make those connections,
نحن نجد الانماط و نصنع هذه الروابط
whether it's Pavlov's dog here
سواء كان كلب بافلوف هنا
associating the sound of the bell with the food,
يربط بين صوت الجرس و الطعام
and then he salivates to the sound of the bell,
فيسيل لعابه لسماعه صوت الجرس
or whether it's a Skinnerian rat,
أو كان جرذ سكينري (نسبة الى قفص سكينر)
in which he's having an association
حيث ينشأ لديه ربط
between his behavior and a reward for it,
بين سلوكه و المكافأة على ذلك السلوك
and therefore he repeats the behavior.
وبالتالي يكرر ذلك السلوك
In fact, what Skinner discovered
في الواقع، ما اكتشفه سكينر
is that, if you put a pigeon in a box like this,
هو انه اذا قمت بوضع حمامة في قفص كهذا
and he has to press one of these two keys,
وكان عليها ان تضغط على احد هذين المفتاحين
and he tries to figure out what the pattern is,
و تحاول معرفة النمط هنا
and you give him a little reward in the hopper box there --
وقمت انت باعطائها مكافأة صغيرة في الصندوق الواثب هناك
if you just randomly assign rewards
ان قمت بتعيين المكافئات عشوائيا
such that there is no pattern,
بحيث تكون غير ذات نمط
they will figure out any kind of pattern.
فانها ستقوم بايجاد اي نوع من الانماط
And whatever they were doing just before they got the reward,
ومهما كانت تفعل قبل لحظات من حصولها على المكافأة
they repeat that particular pattern.
ستكرر ذلك النمط المعين
Sometimes it was even spinning around twice counterclockwise,
احيانا قد يكون دورتين عكس عقارب الساعة
once clockwise and peck the key twice.
مرة باتجاه عقارب الساعة ونقر المفتاح مرتين
And that's called superstition,
وهذا مايسمى بالخرافات
and that, I'm afraid,
و اخشى ان ذلك
we will always have with us.
سيلازمنا دوما
I call this process "patternicity" --
ادعو هذه العملية "بالتنميط"
that is, the tendency to find meaningful patterns
وهو الميل الى ايجاد انماط ذات معنى
in both meaningful and meaningless noise.
في كل ضوضاء ذات معنى او غير ذات معنى
When we do this process, we make two types of errors.
عندما نقوم بهذه العملية، فاننا نقترف نوعين من الاخطاء
A Type I error, or false positive,
النوع الاول الايجابي الزائف
is believing a pattern is real
وهو الاعتقاد بوجود النمط
when it's not.
عندما لا يكون موجودا
Our second type of error is a false negative.
النوع الثاني من الاخطاء هو السلبي الزائف
A Type II error is not believing
خطأ من النوع الثاني وهو عدم تصديق
a pattern is real when it is.
وجود نمط عندما يكون موجودا بالفعل
So let's do a thought experiment.
لذا دعونا نقم بتجربة فكرية
You are a hominid three million years ago
انت من اسلاف البشر قبل ثلاثة ملايين عام
walking on the plains of Africa.
تتمشى على سهول افريقيا
Your name is Lucy, okay?
اسمك لوسي، حسنا؟
And you hear a rustle in the grass.
وتسمع حفيفا بين الاعشاب
Is it a dangerous predator,
هل هو حيوان مفترس خطر،
or is it just the wind?
ام انها الرياح؟
Your next decision could be the most important one of your life.
ان قرارك التالي قد يكون اهم القرارات في حياتك
Well, if you think that the rustle in the grass is a dangerous predator
حسنا، ان اعتقدت ان الحفيف بين الاعشاب هو لحيوان مفترس خطر
and it turns out it's just the wind,
و تبين انها الرياح
you've made an error in cognition,
فقد ارتكبت خطأ في الادراك
made a Type I error, false positive.
قد ارتكبت خطأ من النوع الاول، الايجابي الزائف.
But no harm. You just move away.
ولكن لا ضرر هنا فقط ابتعدت بعيدا
You're more cautious. You're more vigilant.
كنت اكثر حذرا و اكثر يقظة.
On the other hand, if you believe that the rustle in the grass is just the wind,
من جانب اخر، ان اعتقدت ان الحفيف بين الاعشاب ليس سوى الرياح
and it turns out it's a dangerous predator,
وتبين انه حيوان مفترس خطر
you're lunch.
كنت انت الغداء
You've just won a Darwin award.
لقد حصلت للتو على جائزة داروين
You've been taken out of the gene pool.
وقد اخرجت من بركة الجينات
Now the problem here is that
و المشكلة الان هي ان
patternicities will occur whenever the cost
التنميط سيحدث كلما كان تكلفة
of making a Type I error
ارتكاب خطأ من النوع الاول
is less than the cost of making a Type II error.
اقل من تكلفة ارتكاب خطأ من النوع الثاني
This is the only equation in the talk by the way.
بالمناسبة هذه هي المعادلة الوحيدة في هذا الحديث
We have a pattern detection problem
لدينا مشكلة الكشف عن نمط
that is assessing the difference between a Type I and a Type II error
و هي تقدير الفرق بين نوعي الاخطاء الاول و الثاني
is highly problematic,
مما يشكل معضلة كبيرة
especially in split-second, life-and-death situations.
خاصة في حالات الحياة او الموت في جزء من الثانية.
So the default position
لذلك كان الخيار الافتراضي
is just: Believe all patterns are real --
هو "تصديق ان كل الانماط حقيقية"
All rustles in the grass are dangerous predators
"كل حفيف بين الاعشاب هو لحيوان مفترس خطر"
and not just the wind.
وليس فقط الرياح"
And so I think that we evolved ...
ولهذا اعتقد اننا تطورنا...
there was a natural selection for the propensity for our belief engines,
هنالك انتقاء طبيعي لميول محركات الاعتقاد لدينا
our pattern-seeking brain processes,
تسعى ادمغتنا الباحثة عن الانماط
to always find meaningful patterns
دوما الى ايجاد انماط ذات معنى
and infuse them with these sort of
و تبثها مع هذا النوع من
predatory or intentional agencies that I'll come back to.
الوساطات المدبرة او المتعمدة التي سأعود اليها
So for example, what do you see here?
على سبيل المثال، ماذا ترى هنا؟
It's a horse head, that's right.
انه رأس حصان، صحيح.
It looks like a horse. It must be a horse.
يبدو كحصان. لابد انه حصان.
That's a pattern.
هذا نمط
And is it really a horse?
هل هو حقا حصان؟
Or is it more like a frog?
ام انه اقرب الى ضفدع؟
See, our pattern detection device,
أترون، جهازنا للكشف عن الانماط،
which appears to be located in the anterior cingulate cortex --
الذي يبدو انه موجود في القشرة الحزامية الامامية
it's our little detection device there --
انه جهاز الكشف لدينا هناك
can be easily fooled, and this is the problem.
يمكن خداعه بسهولة، وهنا تكمن المشكلة
For example, what do you see here?
على سبيل المثال، ماذا ترى هنا؟
Yes, of course, it's a cow.
نعم، بالطبع انها بقرة
Once I prime the brain -- it's called cognitive priming --
حالما أهيئ العقل -- مايسمى بالتهيئة الادراكية--
once I prime the brain to see it,
حالما أعد العقل ليراها،
it pops back out again even without the pattern that I've imposed on it.
فانها تظهر من جديد حتى من دون النمط الذي فرضته عليها
And what do you see here?
و ماذا ترى هنا؟
Some people see a Dalmatian dog.
بعض الناس يرون كلبا دلماسيا
Yes, there it is. And there's the prime.
نعم، هاهو. و هاهو الاعداد
So when I go back without the prime,
لذلك عندما اعود دون الاعداد
your brain already has the model
فان عقلك لديه النموذج مسبقا
so you can see it again.
لذلك يمكنك ان تراه مجددا
What do you see here?
ماذا ترون هنا؟
Planet Saturn. Yes, that's good.
كوكب ساترن، نعم هذا صحيح
How about here?
ماذا عن هنا؟
Just shout out anything you see.
قولو بصوت عالي ماترونه
That's a good audience, Chris.
انه جمهور جيد، كريس
Because there's nothing in this. Well, allegedly there's nothing.
لأنه لايوجد شيء هنا، حسنا يزعم انه لا شيء هنا.
This is an experiment done by Jennifer Whitson
هذه تجربة قامت بها جنيفر وتسون
at U.T. Austin
بجامعة تكساس اوستن
on corporate environments
في بيئات الشركات
and whether feelings of uncertainty and out of control
عما اذا كانت مشاعر من عدم اليقين والخروج عن السيطرة
makes people see illusory patterns.
تجعل الناس يرون انماط وهمية
That is, almost everybody sees the planet Saturn.
ذلك ان معظم الناس يرون كوكب ساترن.
People that are put in a condition of feeling out of control
اما من وضعوا في حالة من الشعور الخارج عن السيطرة
are more likely to see something in this,
من الارجح انهم يرون شيئا ما فيه
which is allegedly patternless.
مما يزعم انه عديم النمط
In other words, the propensity to find these patterns
بعبارة اخرى، ان الميل الى البحث عن هذه الأنماط
goes up when there's a lack of control.
يرتفع عندما يكون هناك نقص في السيطرة
For example, baseball players are notoriously superstitious
على سبيل المثال، يعرف لاعبو البيسبول بايمانهم بالخرافات
when they're batting,
عندما يضربون الكرة
but not so much when they're fielding.
ولكن ليس كثيرا عندما يعدون في الميدان
Because fielders are successful
لان العدائين ناجحون
90 to 95 percent of the time.
بنسبة 90 الى 95 في المائة
The best batters fail seven out of 10 times.
افضل ضاربي الكرة يخطؤون سبعة من اصل عشرة مرات
So their superstitions, their patternicities,
لذلك فان خرافاتهم و تنميطهم
are all associated with feelings of lack of control
كلها مرتبطة بمشاعر نقص السيطرة
and so forth.
وهكذا دواليك
What do you see in this particular one here, in this field?
ماذا ترون هنا تحديدا، في هذا المجال؟
Anybody see an object there?
هل يرى احدكم شيئا هنا؟
There actually is something here,
هنالك في الحقيقة شيئ ما هنا،
but it's degraded.
ولكنه متحلل
While you're thinking about that,
اثناء تفكيركم في ذلك،
this was an experiment done by Susan Blackmore,
كانت هذه تجربة قامت بها سوزان بلاكمور
a psychologist in England,
طبيبة نفسية في انجلترا
who showed subjects this degraded image
عرضت هذه الصورة على اشخاص
and then ran a correlation between
ثم ربطت بين
their scores on an ESP test:
علاماتهم في اختبار الادراك فوق الحسي
How much did they believe in the paranormal,
الى اي مدي يؤمنون بالخوارق،
supernatural, angels and so forth.
مافوق الطبيعة، الملائكة وما الى ذلك
And those who scored high on the ESP scale,
هؤلاء الذين احرزو علامات متقدمة في اختبار الادراك فوق الحسي
tended to not only see
كانو يميلون ليس فقط الى رؤية
more patterns in the degraded images
انماط اكثر في الصورة المتحللة
but incorrect patterns.
و انما انماط غير صحيحة
Here is what you show subjects.
هذا ما تعرضه على الاشخاص
The fish is degraded 20 percent, 50 percent
السمكة متحللة بنسبة 20 في المائة، 50 في المائة
and then the one I showed you,
ثم التي عرضتها لكم
70 percent.
70في المائة
A similar experiment was done by another [Swiss] psychologist
تجربة مماثلة قام بها طبيب نفسي سويسري.
named Peter Brugger,
يدعى بيتر بروغير
who found significantly more meaningful patterns
وجد زيادة ملحوظة للانماط التي لها معنى
were perceived on the right hemisphere,
تصور في الجانب الايمن للدماغ
via the left visual field, than the left hemisphere.
عبر المجال البصري الايسر، اكثر من الجانب الايسر
So if you present subjects the images such
لذلك ان قمت بعرض صور على اشخاص وكانت
that it's going to end up on the right hemisphere instead of the left,
ستنتهي على الجانب الايمن من الدماغ بدلا عن الايسر
then they're more likely to see patterns
فانهم اكثر عرضة لرؤية الأنماط
than if you put it on the left hemisphere.
من انك اذا وضعتها على الجانب الأيسر
Our right hemisphere appears to be
يبدو ان نصف دماغنا الايمن
where a lot of this patternicity occurs.
حيث الكثير من التنميط (البحث عن الانماط) يحدث هناك
So what we're trying to do is bore into the brain
مانحاول فعله هو ان نحفر في الدماغ
to see where all this happens.
لنرى أين يحدث كل هذا
Brugger and his colleague, Christine Mohr,
بروغير و زميلته كريستين مور
gave subjects L-DOPA.
اعطو اشخاصا ال-دوبا
L-DOPA's a drug, as you know, given for treating Parkinson's disease,
ال-دوبا هو عقار، كما تعلمون، يعطى لمعالجة مرض باركينسون (الشلل الرعاش)
which is related to a decrease in dopamine.
الذي يرتبط بنقص الدوبامين
L-DOPA increases dopamine.
ال-دوبا يزيد مستوى الدوبامين
An increase of dopamine caused
وزيادة الدوبامين تسببت
subjects to see more patterns
في زيادة رؤية الاشخاص للأنماط
than those that did not receive the dopamine.
اكثر من الذين لم يحصلو على الدوبامين
So dopamine appears to be the drug
اذن يبدو ان الدوبامين هو العقار
associated with patternicity.
المرتبط بالتنميط
In fact, neuroleptic drugs
في الواقع، ان ادوية الذهان
that are used to eliminate psychotic behavior,
التي تستخدم للقضاء على السلوك الذهاني
things like paranoia, delusions
اشياء كجنون الاضطهاد، الاوهام
and hallucinations,
و الهلوسات
these are patternicities.
كل هذه نمطيات
They're incorrect patterns. They're false positives. They're Type I errors.
انماط خاطئة. ايجابية زائفة. انها اخطاء من النوع الاول
And if you give them drugs
وعندما تعطيهم الادوية
that are dopamine antagonists,
التي هي مضادات الدوبامين
they go away.
فانها تزول
That is, you decrease the amount of dopamine,
ذلك انك تقلل مستوى الدوبامين
and their tendency to see
وبالتالي ميولهم لرؤية
patterns like that decreases.
انماط كتلك تقل ايضا
On the other hand, amphetamines like cocaine
من ناحية اخرى، الامفيتامينات مثل الكوكايين
are dopamine agonists.
مضادات للدوبامين
They increase the amount of dopamine.
تقلل مستوى الدوبامين
So you're more likely to feel in a euphoric state,
لذلك على الارجح تشعر في حالة من النشوة
creativity, find more patterns.
بالابداع اكثر وستجد الكثير من الانماط
In fact, I saw Robin Williams recently
في الواقع، لقد رأيت روبن ويليم مؤخرا
talk about how he thought he was much funnier
يتحدث عن كيف انه كان يظن انه اكثر مرحا و تسلية
when he was doing cocaine, when he had that issue, than now.
عندما كان يتعاطى الكوكايين، عندما كانت لديه تلك المسألة، من الان
So perhaps more dopamine
لذا ربما زيادة الدوبامين
is related to more creativity.
مرتبطة بزيادة الابداع
Dopamine, I think, changes
الدوبامين، اعتقد انه يغير
our signal-to-noise ratio.
نسبة المؤشر-الى-الضجيج لدينا
That is, how accurate we are
وهي مدى دقتنا
in finding patterns.
في العثور على الانماط
If it's too low, you're more likely to make too many Type II errors.
اذا انخفض كثيرا، فعلى الارجح انك سترتكب الكثير من الاخطاء من النوع الثاني
You miss the real patterns. You don't want to be too skeptical.
ستفوت الانماط الحقيقية، لانك لاتريد ان تكون متشككا للغاية
If you're too skeptical, you'll miss the really interesting good ideas.
ان كنت متشككا جدا، ستفوتك الأفكار الجيدة المثيرة للاهتمام
Just right, you're creative, and yet you don't fall for too much baloney.
للحق، انت مبدع ومع ذالك لا تعجب بالكثير من الهراء
Too high and maybe you see patterns everywhere.
رفيع المستوى وربما ترى انماطا في كل مكان
Every time somebody looks at you, you think people are staring at you.
في كل مرة ينظر اليك احد ما، تظن ان الناس يحدقون بك
You think people are talking about you.
تظن ان الناس يتكلمون عنك
And if you go too far on that, that's just simply
و ان تماديت في هذا، هذا ببساطة
labeled as madness.
مايوصف بالجنون
It's a distinction perhaps we might make
انه تمييز ربما يجب ان نقوم به
between two Nobel laureates, Richard Feynman
بين اثنين من الحائزين على جائزة نوبل، ريتشارد فاينمان
and John Nash.
و جون ناش.
One sees maybe just the right number
احدهما يرى ربما العدد الصحيح بالتحديد
of patterns to win a Nobel Prize.
من الانماط للفوز بجائزة نوبل
The other one also, but maybe too many patterns.
الاخر ايضا لكن ربما الكثير من الانماط
And we then call that schizophrenia.
فنسمي ذلك الفصام
So the signal-to-noise ratio then presents us with a pattern-detection problem.
هذا يعني ان نسبة المؤشر-الى-الضوضاء تقدم لنا مشكلة مع الكشف عن نمط
And of course you all know exactly
و بالطبع كلكم تعلمون جيدا
what this is, right?
ماهذا، صحيح.
And what pattern do you see here?
اي نمط ترون هنا؟
Again, I'm putting your anterior cingulate cortex to the test here,
مرة اخرى، انا اختبر القشرة الحزامية الامامية لديكم هنا
causing you conflicting pattern detections.
مسببا لكم تضاربا في الكشف عن الانماط هنا
You know, of course, this is Via Uno shoes.
تعلمون بالطبع، ان هذه احذية فيا اونو
These are sandals.
انها صنادل
Pretty sexy feet, I must say.
قدمين مثيرتين جدا، يجب ان اقول
Maybe a little Photoshopped.
ربما خضعت للقليل من الفوتوشوب
And of course, the ambiguous figures
وبالطبع تلك الاجسام المبهمة
that seem to flip-flop back and forth.
التي يبدو انها تتقلب ذهابا و ايابا
It turns out what you're thinking about a lot
تعكس ماتفكر فيه كثيرا
influences what you
وتعزز
tend to see.
ما تميل الى رؤيته
And you see the lamp here, I know.
وترون المصباح هنا، اعلم ذلك
Because the lights on here.
لأنه مضاء هنا
Of course, thanks to the environmentalist movement
بطبيعة الحال، وبفضل الحركات المناصرة للبيئة
we're all sensitive to the plight of marine mammals.
كلنا حساسون تجاه محنة الثديات البحرية
So what you see in this particular ambiguous figure
لذلك ما ترونه هنا تحديدا في هذا الشكل المبهم
is, of course, the dolphins, right?
هي الدولفينات، صحيح
You see a dolphin here,
ترون الدولفين هنا
and there's a dolphin,
ها هو دولفين
and there's a dolphin.
وها هو دولفين
That's a dolphin tail there, guys.
انه ذيل دولفين هناك، شباب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If we can give you conflicting data, again,
لو امكننا ان نعطيكم بيانات متضاربة مرة اخرى
your ACC is going to be going into hyperdrive.
فان الايه سي سي لديكم (القشرة الحزامية الامامية) ستصاب بفرط التشغيل
If you look down here, it's fine. If you look up here, then you get conflicting data.
اذا نظرتم هنا في الاسفل، لا بأس. اذا نظرتم هنا بالاعلى تحصلون على تضارب في البيانات
And then we have to flip the image
عندها يجب ان نقلب الصورة
for you to see that it's a set up.
لترو انها معدة مسبقا
The impossible crate illusion.
وهم القفص المستحيل
It's easy to fool the brain in 2D.
من السهل خداع العقل في بعدين
So you say, "Aw, come on Shermer, anybody can do that
ستقولون " هيا دعك من هذا يا شيرمر، اي شخص يمكن ان يفعل ذلك
in a Psych 101 text with an illusion like that."
بكتاب ملخص لعلم النفس و خدعة كتلك"
Well here's the late, great Jerry Andrus'
حسنا هاهو الراحل العظيم جيري اندروس
"impossible crate" illusion in 3D,
وهم القفص المستحيل في ثلاثة ابعاد
in which Jerry is standing inside
وفيه يقف جيري داخل
the impossible crate.
القفص المستحيل
And he was kind enough to post this
وقد تفضل و قدم هذا العرض
and give us the reveal.
و كشف لنا
Of course, camera angle is everything. The photographer is over there,
بالطبع زوايا الكاميرا هي كل شيء. هاهو المصور هناك
and this board appears to overlap with this one, and this one with that one, and so on.
ويبدو ان هذا اللوح يتداخل مع هذا، وهذا مع ذاك، وهكذا
But even when I take it away,
ولكن حتى عندما ابعدها بعيدا
the illusion is so powerful because of how are brains are wired
فان الوهم قوي جدا بسبب كيف ان عقولنا تجتهد في البحث
to find those certain kinds of patterns.
للعثور على هذا النوع من الانماط
This is a fairly new one
هذه واحدة جديدة نوعا ما
that throws us off because of the conflicting patterns
تذهلنا بسبب الانماط المتضاربة
of comparing this angle with that angle.
لمقارنة هذه الزاوية بتلك الزاوية
In fact, it's the exact same picture side by side.
في الواقع، هي نفس الصورة جنبا الى جنب
So what you're doing is comparing that angle
اذن ماتفعلونه هو مقارنة تلك الزاوية
instead of with this one, but with that one.
بهذه بدلا عن تلك
And so your brain is fooled.
وبهذا تنخدع عقولكم
Yet again, your pattern detection devices are fooled.
و بالتالي تنخدع اجهزة الكشف عن الانماط لديكم
Faces are easy to see
من السهل رؤية الوجوه
because we have an additional evolved
لأن لدينا برمجيات اضافية متطورة
facial recognition software
لتمييز الوجوه
in our temporal lobes.
داخل الفصوص الصدغية للمخ لدينا
Here's some faces on the side of a rock.
هذه بعض الوجوه على جانب صخرة
I'm actually not even sure if this is -- this might be Photoshopped.
في الحقيقة لست حتى متأكدا من انها-- قد تكون معدة ببرنامج فوتوشوب.
But anyway, the point is still made.
على اية حال، وجهة النظر ما تزال قائمة
Now which one of these looks odd to you?
والان اي واحدة من هذه تبدو لكم غريبة؟
In a quick reaction, which one looks odd?
في رد فعل سريع، اي واحدة تبدو غريبة؟
The one on the left. Okay. So I'll rotate it
التي الى اليسار. حسنا سأقلبها
so it'll be the one on the right.
اذن ستصبح الى اليمين
And you are correct.
انتم محقون
A fairly famous illusion -- it was first done with Margaret Thatcher.
انه وهم شهير جدا -- اجري من قبل مع مارجريت تاتشر
Now, they trade up the politicians every time.
والان يروجون للسياسيين في كل مرة
Well, why is this happening?
حسنا، لماذا يحدث هذا؟
Well, we know exactly where it happens,
نعلم تحديدا اين تحدث
in the temporal lobe, right across, sort of above your ear there,
في الفص الصدغي للدماغ، الذي يوجد نوعا ما فوق اذانكم هناك
in a little structure called the fusiform gyrus.
داخل تكوين صغير يدعى فيوزيوم جايروس
And there's two types of cells that do this,
و هناك نوعان من الخلايا تقوم بهذا
that record facial features either globally,
تسجل ملامح الوجه اما بشكل عام
or specifically these large, rapid-firing cells,
او على وجه التحديد هذه الخلايا الكبيرة سريعة الاطلاق
first look at the general face.
اولا تلقي نظرة على الوجه العام
So you recognize Obama immediately.
فتميز أوباما فورا
And then you notice something quite
ثم تلاحظ شيئا فيه
a little bit odd about the eyes and the mouth.
القليل من الغرابة حول الوجه والعينين
Especially when they're upside down,
خصوصا وانها مقلوبة رأسا على عقب
you're engaging that general facial recognition software there.
انت تشرك تلك البرمجيات للتعرف على الوجوه العامة هناك
Now I said back in our little thought experiment,
والان كنت قد قلت سابقا في تجربتنا الصغيرة للتفكير
you're a hominid walking on the plains of Africa.
انت من اسلاف البشر تتجول في سهول افريقيا
Is it just the wind or a dangerous predator?
هل هي مجرد رياح ام حيوان مفترس خطر؟
What's the difference between those?
ما الفرق بينهما؟
Well, the wind is inanimate;
حسنا، الرياح جماد
the dangerous predator is an intentional agent.
الحيوان المفترس عامل ذو نية
And I call this process agenticity.
و أدعو هذه العملية بالتوكل
That is the tendency to infuse patterns
وهو الميل الى تفعيل الانماط
with meaning, intention and agency,
ذات المعنى، والتي وراءها نية او عامل
often invisible beings from the top down.
غالبا الكائنات الغير مرئية من الاعلى الى الاسفل
This is an idea that we got
هذه فكرة حصلنا عليها
from a fellow TEDster here, Dan Dennett,
من زميل هنا بتيد ، دان دينيت
who talked about taking the intentional stance.
الذي تحدث عن اتخاذ موقف متعمد
So it's a type of that expanded to explain, I think, a lot of different things:
اذن هو نوع من الشرح الموسع اعتقد لتفسير كثير من الاشياء
souls, spirits, ghosts, gods, demons, angels,
النفوس، الأرواح، الالهة، الشياطين، الملائكة
aliens, intelligent designers,
الكائنات الفضائية، المصممون الاذكياء
government conspiracists
مؤامرات الحكومة
and all manner of invisible agents
وكل انواع العوامل الغير مرئية
with power and intention, are believed
ذات القوة و الارادة، يعتقد انها
to haunt our world and control our lives.
تطارد عالمنا وتتحكم بحياتنا
I think it's the basis of animism
اعتقد انه اصل الروحانية
and polytheism and monotheism.
و الشرك والتوحيد
It's the belief that aliens are somehow
انه الاعتقاد ان الكائنات الفضائية بطريقة ما
more advanced than us, more moral than us,
اكثر تقدما منا، اخلاقيون اكثر منا
and the narratives always are
و في الرواية دائما
that they're coming here to save us and rescue us from on high.
يأتون هنا من اعلى لحمايتنا و انقاذنا
The intelligent designer's always portrayed
و يصور المصمم الذكي (مصمم الكون) دائما بأنه
as this super intelligent, moral being
هذا الكائن الاخلاقي خارق الذكاء
that comes down to design life.
الذي ينزل ليصمم الحياة
Even the idea that government can rescue us --
حتى فكرة ان الحكومة قادرة على انقاذنا
that's no longer the wave of the future,
لم تعد موجة المستقبل
but that is, I think, a type of agenticity:
ولكن ذلك اعتقد نوع من التوكل
projecting somebody up there,
المصمم في الاعلى هناك
big and powerful, will come rescue us.
كبير و قوي سيأتي لانقاذنا
And this is also, I think, the basis of conspiracy theories.
اعتقد ايضا ان هذا هو الأصل وراء نظرية المؤامرة
There's somebody hiding behind there pulling the strings,
ان هنالك شخص ما يختبئ في الخلف يحرك الخيوط
whether it's the Illuminati
سواء ان كانو مجموعة المتنورين
or the Bilderbergers.
ام مجموعة بيلدربيرجر.
But this is a pattern detection problem, isn't it?
غير ان هذه مشكلة كشف عن نمط، اليست كذلك
Some patterns are real and some are not.
بعض الانماط حقيقية والبعض الاخر لا
Was JFK assassinated by a conspiracy or by a lone assassin?
هل تم اغتيال جون اف كيندي نتيجة مؤامرة ام على يد قاتل وحيد؟
Well, if you go there -- there's people there on any given day --
حسنا، هنالك اشخاص في كل يوم
like when I went there, here -- showing me where the different shooters were.
مثل عندما ذهبت هناك، هنا يبينون لي اين كان مختلف الرماة
My favorite one was he was in the manhole.
المفضلة لدي انه كان داخل فتحة التصريف الصحي
And he popped out at the last second, took that shot.
و قفز خارجا في اخر ثانية و اطلق تلك الرصاصة
But of course, Lincoln was assassinated by a conspiracy.
ولكن بالطبع اغتيال لينكولن كان مؤامرة
So we can't just uniformly dismiss
اذن لايمكننا فقط استبعاد بشكل موحد
all patterns like that.
كل الانماط هكذا
Because, let's face it, some patterns are real.
لانه، دعونا نواجه ذلك، بعض الانماط حقيقية
Some conspiracies really are true.
بعض المؤامرات حقيقية بالفعل
Explains a lot, maybe.
مما يفسر الكثير، ربما
And 9/11 has a conspiracy theory. It is a conspiracy.
للحادي عشر من سبتمبر نظرية مؤامرة. انها مؤامرة
We did a whole issue on it.
قمنا باصدار عدد كامل عنها
Nineteen members of Al Queda plotting to fly planes into buildings
تسعة عشر عضوا في تنظيم القاعدة خططو لضرب مباني بالطائرات
constitutes a conspiracy.
مما يشكل مؤامرة
But that's not what the "9/11 truthers" think.
ولكن هذا ليس مايعتقده محققو 11/9
They think it was an inside job by the Bush administration.
يعتقدون انها عمل داخلي لادارة بوش
Well, that's a whole other lecture.
حسنا، انها محاضرة اخرى كاملة
You know how we know that 9/11
لكن هل تعلمون كيف نعلم نحن ان 9/11
was not orchestrated by the Bush administration?
لم تكن مدبرة بواسطة ادارة بوش؟
Because it worked.
لانها نجحت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So we are natural-born dualists.
اذن نحن اثنينيون بالفطرة (الايمان ان الانسان ذو جسد و روح)
Our agenticity process comes from
عملية التوكل لدينا تأتي من
the fact that we can enjoy movies like these.
واقع اننا نستمتع بافلام كهذه
Because we can imagine, in essence,
لانه يمكننا ان نتخيل، في الجوهر
continuing on.
الاستمرار
We know that if you stimulate the temporal lobe,
نعلم انه اذا حفزت الفص الصدغي
you can produce a feeling of out-of-body experiences,
يمكنك ان توجد حالة من تجربة خارج-الجسم
near-death experiences,
تجربة على-وشك-الموت
which you can do by just touching an electrode to the temporal lobe there.
التي يمكنك ان تقوم بها فقط بملامسة قطب كهربائي للفص هناك
Or you can do it through loss of consciousness,
او يمكنك ان تقوم بها بفقد الوعي
by accelerating in a centrifuge.
عن طريق جهاز الطرد المركزي
You get a hypoxia, or a lower oxygen.
ستصاب بنقص الاوكسجين
And the brain then senses
سيشعر الدماغ عندها
that there's an out-of-body experience.
بحالة من الخروج من الجسم
You can use -- which I did, went out and did --
يمكنك ان تستعمل --كما فعلت انا هناك--
Michael Persinger's God Helmet,
خوذة مايكل بيرسنجر (خوذة الرب)
that bombards your temporal lobes with electromagnetic waves.
التي تمطر فصك الصدغي بوابل من الموجات الكهرومغناطيسية
And you get a sense of out-of-body experience.
فتشعر بتجربة احساس خارج الجسم
So I'm going to end here with a short video clip
في الختام سانهي هذا بمقطع من الفيديو هنا
that sort of brings all this together.
سيفسر نوعا ما كل هذا
It's just a minute and a half.
انه لمدة دقيقة و نصف فقط
It ties together all this into the power of expectation and the power of belief.
يربط كل هذا مع قوة التوقع و قوة الايمان
Go ahead and roll it.
هيا اديروه
Narrator: This is the venue they chose for their fake auditions
المعلق: هذا هو المكان الذي اختاروه لاجراء اختباراتهم الوهمية
for an advert for lip balm.
لاعلان عن مرطب شفاه
Woman: We're hoping we can use part of this
المراة: نامل ان نستعمل جزء من هذا
in a national commercial, right?
في اعلان تجاري محلي، صحيح
And this is test on some lip balms
وهذا اختبار على نوع من مرطب الشفاه
that we have over here.
لدينا هنا
And these are our models who are going to help us,
وهؤلاء عارضونا سيقومون بمساعدتنا
Roger and Matt.
روجر و مات
And we have our own lip balm,
ولدينا مرطب الشفاه خاصتنا
and we have a leading brand.
ولدينا اخر من علامة تجارية رائدة
Would you have any problem
هل لديك اي مشكلة
kissing our models to test it?
في تقبيل عارضينا لاختباره
Girl: No.
الفتاة: لا
Woman: You wouldn't? (Girl: No.) Woman: You'd think that was fine.
المرأة: هل تمانعين؟ (الفتاة: لا) المرأة: تعتقدين انه لابأس بذلك
Girl: That would be fine. (Woman: Okay.)
الفتاة: لا بأس بذلك. (المرأة: حسنا)
So this is a blind test.
هذا الاختبار مع اغماض العينين
I'm going to ask you to go ahead
ساطلب منك ان تتقدمي
and put a blindfold on.
وتضعي عصابة للعينين
Kay, now can you see anything? (Girl: No.)
حسنا، هل يمكنك ان تري شيئا؟ (الفتاة: لا)
Pull it so you can't even see down. (Girl: Okay.)
اسحبيها حتى لا تري حتى من الاسفل. (الفتاة: حسنا)
Woman: It's completely blind now, right?
المرأة: الان لا ترين شيئا على الاطلاق، صحيح؟
Girl: Yes. (Woman: Okay.)
الفتاة: نعم. المرأة (حسنا)
Now, what I'm going to be looking for in this test
الان، ما ابحث عنه انا في هذا الاختبار
is how it protects your lips,
هو كيف سيحمي شفتيك
the texture, right,
الملمس (القوام)، صحيح
and maybe if you can discern any flavor or not.
و ربما ان كنت تستطيعين تميز اي نكهة ام لا
Girl: Okay. (Woman: Have you ever done a kissing test before?)
الفتاة: حسنا. (المرأة: هل قمت باختبار تقبيل من قبل؟)
Girl: No.
الفتاة: لا
Woman: Take a step here.
المرأة: تقدمي خطوة هنا
Okay, now I'm going to ask you to pucker up.
حسنا، الان اريدك ان تضمي شفتيك
Pucker up big and lean in just a little bit, okay?
ضميها اكثر و انحني قليلا حسنا
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Woman: Okay.
حسنا
And, Jennifer, how did that feel?
جينيفر كيف كان شعورك؟
Jennifer: Good.
جينيفر: جيدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Girl: Oh my God!
الفتاة: اه يا الهي
Michael Shermer: Thank you very much. Thank you. Thanks.
مايكل شيرمر: شكرا جزيلا لكم. شكرا. شكرا